本劇改編自聖經  它們曾改變世界，直到如今
本劇將始終保持《聖經》真諦
《聖經》前情提要
Previously on The Bible...
猶太王國是由偉大的英雄們一手建立
Great heroes have forged the Jewish nation in faith.
諾亞拯救地上的生物免遭洪水
Noah saved life on earth from the flood.
上帝警告我  要我造一艘船
God warned me. He told me to build a boat.
亞伯拉罕成為萬國之父
Abraham became the father of God's nation.
亞伯拉罕
Abraham!
摩西解放子民  帶他們擺脫埃及人的奴役
Moses freed the people from Egyptian slavery.
主啊
Lord!
跟我走
Follow me!
然後  他頒布了上帝的法典
Then, he delivered God's laws.
我們有可以助我們奪下應許之地的新法典了
We have new laws preparing us for the Promised Land.
偉大的大衛王團結以色列人
The great King David united the Israelites...
以色列
Israel!
攻下了耶路撒冷
and won the city of Jerusalem.
但因被超級大國圍困
But surrounded by superpowers,
以色列一直為自身的存亡不斷抗爭
Israel's survival was a constant struggle.
然後羅馬帝國攻占了應許之地
Then Rome conquered the Promised Land.
人們渴望大衛王再世  出現新的救世主
People long for a new King David, a savior.
有人認為那人便是施洗約翰
Some believed it was John the Baptist.
你已潔凈  所有以色列人也將和你一樣
As you are cleansed, so all Israel shall be cleansed.
人們都成群結隊去找那個野人似的約翰
People are flocking to this wild man, John.
他們認為他是先知
They think he's a prophet.
我只是荒野裡的聲音
I am just a voice in the wilderness,
等待著主的
preparing the way for the...
到來
...Lord.
為我施洗吧
Baptize me!
他將帶來正義與公平的新時代
He will bring a new age of righteousness and justice.
他的力量將帶領人類邁向新世界
His power will draw all men to a new world.
全人類
All people!
耶穌開始招聚門徒
Jesus has started to gather disciples
他們放棄一切跟從他
who give up everthing to follow him.
來跟從我  彼得
Come with me, Peter.
別再捕魚了  我要叫你得人如得魚一樣
Give up catching fish and I will make you a fisher of men.
如今他們與懼怕所有異教的
Now they are on a collision cause
當局站在了對立的兩面
with the temple of authorities who fear any Dissent.
我聽說了一個年輕先知  叫拿撒勒人耶穌
I've had a report of a young prophet, Jesus of Nazareth.
而羅馬人  絕不會容忍此事
And Romans, who won't tolerate.
是時候讓你們明白  主人為你們做了什麼
It's time you understood what your masters do for you.
-我們要做什麼  -改變世界
- What are we going to do? - Change the world.
聖經
加利利
在加利利這個窮鄉僻壤的地方  巨變要來了
In the poor backwater of Galilee, revolution is coming.
世世代代的以色列人都受
For generations, the people of Israel have been guided
猶太教守護者法利賽人的指引
by the Pharisees, guardians of the Jewish faith.
你們必須堅定不移地遵守
You should untiringly keep the commandments
主你的神的誡命和律例
of the Lord your God and his statutes...
法利賽人相信民族的福祉
The Pharisees believe the well-being of the nation
在於嚴格遵守上帝給摩西的法典
depends on strictly observing the laws God gave to Moses.
他們深受人們愛戴
They are loved and admired by the people.
你們必須做正確的事  以及
You should do what is right and what is good
主眼裡正確的事
in sight of the Lord.
你看見他了嗎  就在那裡
Have you seen him? Over there!
但耶穌提供了一種新的方式
But Jesus offers a new way...
所以主吩咐我們要遵守所有律法
So the Lord commanded us to observe all these statutes...
是耶穌
It's Jesus!
這邊  約翰  一直往前走不要停
This way, John. Keep everyone moving.
本字幕由YYeTs人人影視翻譯第一版
由Matt K Fu 以基督徒角度作編修
僅供學習 禁止用於任何商業盈利行為
翻譯：sakura櫻  CiciXT  賀天天
翻譯：小琪777  和小蟹  茶炒栗子
校對：威廉  蓬蓬裙  不要叫我馬維斯
時間軸：魚骨頭  今  不要叫我馬維斯
後期：zzzyusa   總監：不要叫我馬維斯
神的國  我們可用什麼比較呢
How shall we picture the kingdom of God?
它好像一粒芥菜種
It is like a mustard seed...
有人拿去種在田裡
...which a man took and sowed in his field,
比地上的百種都小
the smallest seed in the world.
但種上以後
Yet when planted...
就長起來
...it grows up...
卻比各樣的菜都大
...and becomes the biggest of all plants.
怎麼了
What's going on?
變成了樹  飛鳥也來它的枝上
It becomes a tree where birds can come...
他癱了
He's paralyzed.
...並在此築巢
... and make their nests.
你的罪赦了  孩子
Your sins are forgiven, my son.
你們聽到了嗎
Did you hear that?
他赦了他的罪
He has forgiven his sins.
不是只有神才能赦罪嗎
I thought only God could do that?
這不是僭妄嗎
Isn't that blasphemy?
他懂得的  這就是僭妄
He knows. It is blasphemy.
你是這意思嗎  我的朋友
Is that your wish, my friend?
回答我啊
Well, answer me.
告訴我
Tell me which is easier...
或說  他的罪赦了
...to say his sins are forgiven,
或說
or say...
你起來行走  那一樣容易呢
Get up and walk?
等等
Wait...
人子是有赦罪的權柄的
The Son of Man has authority to forgive sin.
朋友們
Friends!
什麼事
What is this about?
連摩西都不會覺得自己能夠赦他人的罪
Not even Moses himself would've thought he could forgive sin.
你聽到夫子是怎麼說了
You heard what our teacher said.
他到底憑什麼權柄可以這麼做
On what authority does he think he can do this?
就憑他自己的權柄
On his authority.
這是僭妄
That is blasphemy.
只有神才可以赦罪
Only God can forgive sin.
而你的朋友
And your friend
如此扯謊  可能會用石頭打死的
could be stoned for a false claim like this.
這不過才開始罷了
This is just the beginning.
我們走
Let's go.
隨著門徒的增多
With a growing number of disciples,
耶穌從這個城走到那個城
Jesus moves from town to town,
講述著神之國  並不斷創造神跡
teaching about god's kingdom and working miracles.
不潔  污穢  他長了麻風
Unclean, unclean. He's a Leper!
都避開他
Get away from him!
求你了  求你了
Please, please...
別碰他
Don't touch him!
我潔凈了  我潔凈了  我潔凈了
I'm clean, I'm clean. I'm clean!
對有些人來說  耶穌是救世主
Jesus is a savior to some...
看他都做了什麼
Look what he's done!
但對羅馬  他卻是個潛在威脅
...but a potential threat to Rome.
新任羅馬總督本丟．彼拉多
The new Roman governor is Pontius Pilate,
過去是軍人  如今成了一位殘酷的政客
an ex-soldier turned ruthless politician.
停  怎麼了
Halt! What's going on?
你們擋著路了  總督要過去
You're in the way! The Governor needs to pass.
彼拉多可不會等
Pilate won't wait!
還要等很久嗎
Will it be much longer?
很快就好  親愛的
Very soon, my love.
-長官  -這次因何停下
- Prefect... - What's the delay this time?
道中有輛破車  長官
It's a broken cart, sir.
那你們還等什麼  給我處理掉
What are you waiting for? Get it off the road!
搬開  搬開
Let's get it moved! Move it!
彼拉多統治下的猶太人瀕臨爆發
Rebellion simmers amongst Pilate's Jewish subjects,
但他不允許任何破壞羅馬統治
but he allows nothing to disrupt Roman rule...
和羅馬稅收的舉動
...or Roman taxes.
所有稅款必須繳清
All taxes must be paid in full!
我們同為猶太人  他們怎能如此
We're all Jews. How can they live with themselves?
自己人卻為羅馬人賣命  真讓人厭惡
Our own people working for Rome? These people makes me sick.
同流合污之徒  我們走吧
Collaborators. Let's move on.
都是些蠹蟲
They're stinking vermin.
你應該離他們遠一點
You should keep your distance from them.
兩個人
Two men...
去聖殿中禱告
... went to the temple to pray.
一個是偽善的法利賽人
One a Pharisee...
而另一個
... and the other one
是個稅吏
a tax collector.
法利賽人禱告說  神啊
The Pharisee prayed: God...
我感謝你  我不像別人
I thank you that I'm not like other men,
偷盜  奸淫
thieves, adulterers...
也不像這個稅吏
... or this tax collector.
但那稅吏
But the tax collector
連舉目望天也不敢
didn't even look up to heaven.
他說
He said,
神啊
God...
開恩可憐我
have mercy on me,
這個罪人
I'm a sinner.
神祝福了那個稅吏
God blessed the tax collector...
而不是法利賽人
not the Pharisee.
凡自高的  必降為卑
Anyone who praises himself will be humbled,
自卑的  必升為高
and anyone who humbles himself will be praised.
馬太  過來
Matthew...come.
看  現在他甚至叫罪人都跟著他
See, now he even calls the sinners to follow him!
讓人不禁好奇  其他跟他的人
One has to wonder of the sins committed
到底都是怎樣的人
by his other followers.
稅吏！
Tax collectors!
他們心中都沒有一絲善意
There's not a thread of good in any of them.
多馬  耶穌不是為好人而來
Thomas, Jesus has not come for the good,
而是為罪人而來
but for the sinners.
他給人們第二次機會
He gives people a second chance.
我們也應該這樣
We should too.
虛心的人有福了
Blessed are the poor,
《聖經原文》
因為天國是他們的
for theirs is the kingdom of heaven.
溫柔的人有福了
Blessed are the meek,
因為他們必承受地土
for they shall inherit the earth.
清心的人有福了
Blessed are the pure in heart,
因為他們必得見神
for they shall see God.
向他禱告  他必垂聽
Pray to him and he will listen.
我們應如何禱告
And how should we pray?
像這樣
Like this.
我們在天上的父
Our Father who is in heaven,
願人都尊你的名為聖
hallowed be your name.
願你的國降臨
Your kingdom come,
願你的旨意
your will be done,
行在地上  如同行在天上
on earth as it is in heaven.
我們日用的飲食  今日賜給我們
Give us this day our daily bread.
免我們的過犯
And forgive us our trespasses,
如同我們免了人的過犯
as we forgive those who trespass against us.
用石頭打死她  她是個妓女
Stone her! She's a whore!
大家都知道經上是怎麼說的
You know what it says in the Scriptures.
-這裡  -母親
- Here! - Mother!
救我
Please!
-淫婦  -躲開點
- Adulteress! -Go away.
律法命令我們
The law commands us
用石頭砸死這個女人
to stone such a woman.
你怎麼看
What do you say?
這是個陷阱
It's a trap.
我會把我的石頭
I'll give my stone
給第一個敢對我說
to the first man who tells me
自己從未犯過罪的人
that he has never sinned.
謝謝你  謝謝你
Thank you, thank you.
去吧  別再犯罪了
Go, and sin no more.
不能再這樣下去了
This cannot continue.
他嘲弄我們的律法
He ridicules our laws,
侮辱我們祖宗的傳統
insults the traditions of our fathers.
我們苦苦奮斗來的一切
Everything that we have fought so hard for,
我們的信仰
our faith,
我們的社會
our communities,
神賜予我們的一切
everything God has given.
聖殿  耶路撒冷
-該亞法  -尼哥底母
- Caiaphas! - Nicodemus.
我聽說了一個年輕先知
I've had a report of a young prophet,
拿撒勒人耶穌
a Jesus of Nazareth.
他在加利利有一大批追隨者
He has a big following in Galilee.
傳聞說他會來耶路撒冷
It's rumored he'll come to Jerusalem.
加利利
Galilee?
-他能創造神跡  -都這麼吹
- He works miracles. - They all do.
尼哥底母  別擔心
Nicodemus, don't worry,
來自加利利的從來都是小事
nothing important ever came from Galilee!
加利利海
耶穌  耶穌
Jesus! Jesus!
這裡像個清靜地方
Looks like a quiet place.
可以了
That's it.
-栓上  -拉比  我來幫你
- Lock it off. - Rabbi, let me help you.
有幾千人之多
There are thousands of them.
這些都是追隨者
These are the followers.
他們歷經長途跋涉  天色不早了
They've come a long way. It's late.
他們說他們餓了
They say they're hungry.
給他們些食物
Give them food.
拿什麼給
But how?
我們一無所有  只有些魚和餅
We have nothing. Just a few fish and some bread.
把它們給我
Bring them to me.
父  感謝你帶給我們的
Thank you, Father, for what you bring us.
我們的天父養活空中的飛鳥
Our father in heaven feeds the birds of the air.
更何況是你們，不是要給的更多嗎？
How much more will he give to you?
不用擔心日常所需  神會提供我們
Don't worry about daily needs, God will provide.
把神放在第一位  其他一切都將隨之而來
Put God first and everything else will follow.
倘若你渴望公義
If you hunger for righteousness,
你必會飽足，經由我
you will be filled through me.
他說我們祈求
He said ask...
就給我們
...and it will be given.
來自上帝的
From God.
上帝給的  這是上帝給的
From God. It's from God!
彌賽亞  彌賽亞
Messiah! Messiah!
他們希望你做他們的王  猶太人的王
They want you to be their king. King of the Jews!
你可以如軍隊般帶領我們
You can lead us like an army.
我們有能力擊敗羅馬人
We are strong enough to beat the Romans!
不  不應該透過這種方式
No, this is not the way.
不是透過武力
Not by force.
他要去哪兒  怎麼回事
Where is he going? What's wrong?
有五千人前往見他
Five thousand came to see him.
五千人
Five thousand.
現在他們高喊著 "彌賽亞"
Now they shout, "Messiah."
今天那些人民  他們稱你為"王"
The people today, they called you "King",
他們認為你是彌賽亞
they think you are a Messiah.
但你似乎沒理會他們
But you seemed to ignore them.
你不會做我們的王嗎
Aren't you going to be our king?
你們說我是誰
Who do you think I am?
你是神的兒子
You are the Son of God.
彼得  憑你自己的知識是不能說這話的
You can't have known this by what you know of me, Peter.
這是神啟示你的
It has been revealed to you by God.
你是彼得（磐石）
You are Peter,
我要把我的教會建造在這磐石上
and on this rock I will build my church.
明日我會在對岸等你們
Tomorrow I'll meet you on the other shore.
為何他要在我們日漸強盛時離開？
Why did he walk away just when we're getting strong?
彌賽亞是不會這樣離開我們的
Surely a Messiah wouldn't leave us like this.
彌賽亞應該是位勇士
A Messiah should be a warrior,
像大衛一樣的征服者
a conqueror like David.
猶大  暴力不是解決的方式
Judas! Force is not the way.
那麼告訴我彌賽亞的方式什麼
So tell me what the way of the Messiah is?
他與眾不同
He's different.
但是馬利亞  倘若他不是彌賽亞呢
But Mary, what if he's not the one?
我們冒著生命危險  為了什麼
We're risking our lives, for what?
他展示給我們了他的能力
He has shown us his power.
我們要對他有信心
We must have faith in him.
-來吧  -他不會讓我們失望
- Come on. - He'll not fail us.
他說他會在對面等我們  走吧
He said he'd meet us on the other side. Let's go!
把帆放下
Bring the sail down!
把東西都綁緊
Tie everything down!
這太危險了
This is too dangerous!
我們應趁來得及轉頭回去
We should turn back while we still can.
你也聽見他說的話了  他要我們能過去
You heard what he said, he wants us to cross.
那是什麼
What is that?
是鬼怪
It's a ghost!
不  多馬
No, Thomas.
是耶穌
It's Jesus.
他就是彌賽亞
He is the Messiah!
彼得
Peter...
彼得  你在做什麼
Peter, what are you doing?
不要怕
Don't be afraid.
過來
Come.
彼得
Peter!
不
No!
彼得
Peter...
你這小信的人哪
You of little faith.
為什麼疑惑呢
Why did you doubt?
你要堅信不移
You need to be strong.
拿撒勒
馬利亞  他回來了
Mary! He's here!
-誰  -耶穌  他終於回來了
- Who? - Jesus! He's back at last.
自從天使加百列造訪耶穌的母親
Ever since the Angel Gabriel came to Jesus' mother,
她就知曉了兒子真正的使命
she's known her son's true purpose.
現在  人們也即將知曉
It's time for others to learn.
耶穌在會堂裡朗誦了一段
In the synagogue, Jesus reads
當時廣為流傳的經文之一
from one of the most popular scriptures of the time,
該經文預言了彌賽亞的降臨
a prophecy describing the coming of the Messiah.
主的靈在我身上
The Spirit of the Lord is upon me,
因為他用膏  膏我
because he has anointed me
叫我傳福音給貧窮的人
to preach good news to the poor.
差遣我報告被擄的得釋放
He has sent me to declare freedom for the captives,
瞎眼的得看見
and recovery of sight for the blind,
叫那受壓制的得自由
to set free those who are oppressed.
今天
Today...
這經文應驗了
...this scripture is fulfilled.
你說什麼
What are you saying?
你說你已經做成這一切了？
That you have achieved all this?
你說你就是被上帝選中派來人間的彌賽亞嗎
That you are the Messiah, the chosen one sent by God?
不可能
No!
我是說你們應順從上帝的旨意
I'm saying you must accept God's word.
大膽  你這是褻瀆上帝
How dare you? That is sacrilege.
他從未修習過律法  無知得很
He has never studied the law. This man knows nothing!
他的醫治能力源自魔鬼
His healing is the work of demons!
預言開始應驗了
It has begun.
他破壞了我們的信仰
He undermines our faith!
-他甚至招募淫亂的信徒  -彼得
- He recruits adulterers... - Peter!
那邊的臉也由他打
Turn the other cheek.
你會為此付出代價
You'll pay the price for this!
正如你的朋友施洗約翰一樣
Like your friend, John the Baptist!
你還沒聽說吧
You haven't heard, have you?
他已被處死
He was executed.
身首異處
Beheaded!
-他是個好人  -是的  但卻死了
- He was a good man. - Yes, and now he's dead.
請為我施洗
Baptize me.
約翰是我見過最好的良師
John was the greatest teacher I ever knew.
他不僅僅是先知
He was more than a prophet.
我們還要繼續
Our work goes on.
過些日子我們就去耶路撒冷
Soon we go to Jerusalem.
耶路撒冷
Jerusalem?
-操之過急  -也太危險
- It's too soon. - It's too dangerous.
我們還沒預備
We're not ready.
猶大  我們為何聚集於此
Judas, why are we all here?
為了走康庄大道嗎
To take the easy path?
我們必須傳道於耶路撒冷
We must take the message to Jerusalem.
直搗權力核心
Right to the heart of power.
耶路撒冷
彼拉多的宅邸
總督大人  我們需要您  有麻煩了
Prefect, you're needed. There's trouble.
羅馬渣滓  羅馬強盜  要他們好看
Roman scum! Roman thieves! Let's show them!
羅馬強盜
Roman thieves!
為大祭司讓路
Make way for the high priest!
馬勒古  馬勒古  發生何事
Malchus! Malchus, what's happening?
又發生了抗議  大祭司
It's another protest, high priest.
我們得帶您離開這兒  抗議正演變成暴動
We need to get you out of here, it's turning into a riot.
將大人送回宅邸  越快越好
Get the master back to his residence. Quick as you can!
-怎麼回事  -是水溝惹的禍
- What is all this about? - The aqueduct.
羅馬人動用了我們的聖殿奉獻去挖水溝
The people are furious that the Romans used our temple funds
民眾非常憤怒
to build it.
上百民眾正要去向彼拉多告狀
Hundreds are heading to complain to Pilate.
什麼
What?
他們還沒靠近他就會被殺了！
He'll have them cut down before they can get anywhere near him.
他曾承諾會聽取民眾的不滿
He said he'd listen to their grievances.
這是個圈套  尼哥底母  你看不出來嗎
It's a trap, Nicodemus! Can't you see that?
盜賊  人渣
Thieves! Scum!
羅馬人渣
Roman scum!
耶路撒冷需要水
Jerusalem needs water.
你們覺得水是你們的神帶來的嗎
You think your God brings it?
不  不是他
No, he does not.
是我們羅馬人帶來的
Rome does.
是時候讓你們明白
It's time you understood
你們的主人為你們做了什麼
what your masters do for you!
彼拉多這是要我們守本分
Pilate's keeping us in our place.
否則想想他會在逾越節做出什麼事來
Imagine what he could do at Passover.
伯大尼村
馬大  出什麼事了
Martha, what's wrong?
我兄弟死了
My brother is dead.
你來得太晚了
You're too late.
帶我去他的墓穴看看
Show me the tomb.
他死去多久了
How long has he been dead?
已經四天了
He's been there four days.
拉撒路...
Lazarus...
復活在我...
I am the resurrection...
生命也在我
...and the life.
信我的人...
Anyone who believes in me...
雖然死了...
...even if he dies...
也必復活
...he will still have life.
拉撒路
Lazarus!
我的兄弟啊
My brother, oh!
凡活著信我的人必永遠不死
Whoever believes in me shall never die.
你若信我就必看見神的榮耀
Believe in me and you will see the glory of God.
該亞法
Caiaphas!
有人說那個耶穌把一個死人救活了
They say this Jesus has raised a man from the dead.
什麼
What?
他會來耶路撒冷過逾越節
He will be here in Jerusalem for Passover.
不行
No.
但如果他與萬千擁護者相伴而來
But if he comes with thousands of supporters,
隨著慶祝節日的人們相繼到來
the city will already be breaking at the seams
這城將會人滿為患
with those arriving for the festival.
尼哥底母 你說得對
Nicodemus, you are right.
到時羅馬人就會插手了
The Romans will step in.
我們必須阻止這個神棍  這個騙子
We must not allow this miracle man, this fraud,
來破壞逾越節
to disrupt Passover.
這事彼拉多知道嗎
Does Pilate know?
《聖經》下集預告
Next time on the Bible
他現在在哪兒
Where is he now?
他剛騎著驢...進了城門
He's just entered the gate. On a donkey.
長官  一個猶太人正在聖殿裡制造麻煩
Sir, a Jew has been causing trouble in the temple.
-他說什麼  -所有廟石都不會再矗立
- He said what?  - Not one stone will be left standing.
毀了這殿  我會在三日之內重新建立起來
Destroy this temple and I will build it again in three days.
如果一場騷亂
If the disturbances that took place a day
在第二天依然繼續的話
are repeated tomorrow,
我將立刻關閉聖殿
I will shut the temple immediately.
取消逾越節
There will be no Passover.
整個城市實行宵禁
I will put this city under curfew.
我說得夠明白了嗎
Do I make myself absolutely clear?
你們只有一位父  就是天父
You only have one Father, and he is in heaven.
你們只有一位夫子  就是基督
You only have one Teacher, and he is the Christ.
就是那個人  那兒
That man, there.
他想要幫助我們
He wants to help us.
他可能會有用
That could be useful.
猶大
Judas.
你們找他有什麼事
What do you want with him?
就是談談
Just a talk.
這是我死前我們在一起的
This is our last meal together,
最後一餐了
before I die.
寬恕我
Spare me.
叛徒
Traitor.
快跑
Run!
-耶穌被抓了  -被抓了  在晚上被抓了
- Jesus has been arrested.  - Arrested? At night?
如果他真的是人們所說的那個人呢
What if he really is what they say he is?
裁決結果只有一個
There is only one verdict,
處死
the sentence is death.